Şaziye Betül Özateş

CONTACT

Institute for Data Science and AI

Information Boğaziçi University

Güney Kampüs, Bebek 34342 İstanbul, Turkey +90 (506) 313-7409

saziye.ozates@boun.edu.tr

linkedin.com/in/şaziye-betül-özateş-a86982211

RESEARCH INTERESTS Natural language processing, deep learning, machine learning, computational linguistics, artificial intelligence.

ABOUT

I am a computer scientist who specializes in natural language processing and machine learning. I have received my bachelor's degree, and master's degree from the Department of Computer Engineering in Boğaziçi University. I completed my PhD studies in the same place under the guidance of Dr. Arzucan Özgür and Dr. Tunga Güngör. From 2020 to 2022, I was a researcher at the Institute of Natural Language Processing at the University of Stuttgart and worked as a post-doctoral research fellow at KUIS-AI Center between 2022 and 2023. Currently, I am an assistant professor at the Institute for Data Science and Artificial Intelligence at Boğaziçi University.

I worked on various computational linguistics, machine learning, and data mining projects throughout my career. My current research focuses on syntactic and semantic analysis of natural language data with the help of various deep learning methods.

EXPERIENCE

Assistant Professor - Full Time

DSAI, Boğaziçi University, 2023-

Research Fellow - Full Time

KUIS AI Center, 2022-2023

Researcher - Full Time

University of Stuttgart, 2020-2022

Teaching Assistant - Part Time

Boğaziçi University, 2015-2016, 2020

Research Assistant - Full Time

Turkish-German University, 2016-2018

EDUCATION

Boğaziçi University, İstanbul, Turkey

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering, May 2022

- Thesis Topic: Deep Learning-based Dependency Parsing for Turkish
- Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Arzucan Özgür and Prof. Tunga Güngör
- Earned 4.0 GPA on 4.0 scale in coursework

Boğaziçi University, İstanbul, Turkey

M.S. in Computer Engineering, June 2014

- Thesis Topic: Multi-document Summarization using Dependency Grammars
- Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Arzucan Özgür
- Earned 4.0 GPA on 4.0 scale in coursework

Boğaziçi University, İstanbul, Turkey

B.S. in Computer Engineering, June 2012

- Senior Project Topic: A Comparison of Financial Time Series Forecasting Using Multilayer Perceptron, Support Vector Machines, and Bayesian Network
- Advisor: Prof. Fikret Gürgen
- Highest honors in Engineering Faculty
- Ranked 2^{nd} in graduating class with 3.64 GPA on 4.0 scale

Publications

Refereed International Journal Papers

Özateş, Ş. B., Özgür, A., Güngör, T., Öztürk, B. (2022). "A Hybrid Approach to Dependency Parsing: Combining Rules and Morphology with Deep Learning." *IEEE Access*, 10, 93867-93886.

Türk, U., Atmaca, F., Özateş, Ş. B. et al. (2022). "Resources for Turkish Dependency Parsing: Introducing the BOUN Treebank and the BoAT Annotation Tool." Language Resources Evaluation, 56(1), 259-307.

Refereed International Conference Papers

Özateş, Ş. B., Özgür, A., Güngör, T., Çetinoğlu, Ö. (2022). "Improving Code-Switching Dependency Parsing with Semi-Supervised Auxiliary Tasks." Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics: NAACL 2022, pp. 1159-1171.

Marşan, B., Akkurt, S. F., Şen, M., Gürbüz, M., Özateş, Ş. B., Üsküdarlı, S., Özgür, A., Güngör, T., Öztürk, B. (2022). "Enhancements to the BOUN Treebank Reflecting the Agglutinative Nature of Turkish." *International Conference on Agglutinative Language Technologies as a challenge of Natural Language Processing (ALTNLP)*, accepted.

Özateş, Ş. B., Çetinoğlu, Ö. (2021). "A Language-aware Approach to Code-switched Morphological Tagging." Proceedings of the Fifth Workshop on Computational Approaches to Linguistic Code-Switching, pp. 72-83. Association for Computational Linguistics.

Türk, U., Bayar, K., Özercan, A. D., Öztürk, G. Y., Özateş, Ş. B. (2020). "First Steps towards Universal Dependencies for Laz." In Proceedings of the Fourth Workshop

on Universal Dependencies (UDW 2020), pp. 189-194. Association for Computational Linguistics.

Türk, U., Atmaca, F., Özateş, Ş. B. et al. (2019). "Improving the Annotations in the Turkish Universal Dependency Treebank." In Universal Dependencies Workshop (UDW 2017) at SyntaxFest 2019, pp. 108-115, Paris, France. Association for Computational Linquistics.

Türk, U., Atmaca, F., Özateş, Ş. B. et al. (2019). "Turkish Treebanking: Unifying and Constructing Efforts." Proceedings of the 13th Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pp. 166-177, Florence, Italy. Association for Computational Linguistics.

Özateş, Ş. B., Özgür, A., Güngör, T., Öztürk, B. (2018). "A Morphology-based Representation Model for LSTM-based Dependency Parsing of Agglutinative Languages." Proceedings of the CoNLL 2018 Shared Task: Multilingual Parsing from Raw Text to Universal Dependencies, pp. 238-247, Brussels, Belgium. Association for Computational Linguistics.

Özateş, Ş. B., Özgür, A., Güngör, Radev, D. R. (2016). "Sentence Similarity based on Dependency Tree Kernels for Multi-document Summarization." Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2016), pp. 2833-2838, Portorož, Slovenia. European Language Resources Association (ELRA).

Thesis

Şaziye Betül Özateş. "Deep Learning-based Dependency Parsing for Turkish", *Ph.D. Thesis, Computer Engineering, Boğaziçi University, İstanbul, Turkey, May 2022.* Thesis Advisors: Assoc. Prof. Arzucan Özgür and Prof. Tunga Güngör.

Şaziye Betül Bilgin. "Multi-document Summarization using Dependency Grammars", M.S. Thesis, Computer Engineering, Boğaziçi University, İstanbul, Turkey, June 2014. Thesis Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Arzucan Özgür.

DFG PROJECT (GERMAN RESEARCH FOUNDATION)

- Computational Structural Analysis of German-Turkish Code-Switching (August 2020 - February 2022)
 - The aim of this project is to analyse Turkish-German code-switching (CS) from a computational perspective. We developed deep learning-based computational models for morphological and syntactic analyses of CS data.

TÜBITAK PROJECTS

- ARDEB 2232 Applications of Deep Learning Architectures for Turkey: GANs for Healthcare (*December 2019 March 2020*)
 - The purpose of this project is investigating generative adversarial network (GAN) structures and proposing deep learning-based solutions for improving the healthcare applications in Turkish.
- ARDEB 1005 A Deep Learning based Turkish Dependency Parser (Feburary 2018 - December 2019)

— We developed a novel state-of-the-art deep learning-based dependency parsing system and created a manually annotated dependency treebank for Turkish. With this system and the newly introduced treebank, we reached the best performance on the dependency parsing task that is needed in many natural language processing applications using deep learning techniques for Turkish.

ATTENDED INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES

- NAACL, 2021 Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, June 6–11, 2021, Online
- ACL, The 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) July 28-August 2, 2019, Florence, Italy
- EMNLP, 2018 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, October 31–November 4, 2018, Brussels, Belgium
- LREC, The 10th edition of the Language Resources and Evaluation Conference, May 23-28, 2016, Portorož, Slovenia

INVITED TALKS

- Şaziye Betül Özateş, "A Semi-supervised Approach for Improving Code-switching Dependency Parsing", Graduate Seminar, Boğaziçi University, Istanbul, Turkey (29 Nov, 2022)
- Şaziye Betül Özateş, "A Semi-supervised Dependency Parsing Approach for Low-resource Languages", CS and AI Talks, Boğaziçi University, Istanbul, Turkey (11 Nov, 2022)
- Şaziye Betül Özateş, "Deep Learning-based Dependency Parsing For Turkish", ClingDing Talks, Indiana University, Bloomington, IN, USA (20 Oct, 2022)
- Şaziye Betül Özateş, "Natural Language Processing for Low-resource Languages using Deep Learning and Linguistic Features", KUIS AI Talks, Koç University, İstanbul, Turkey (18 Jul, 2022)
- Şaziye Betül Özateş, "Improving Dependency Parsing of Turkish: A Hybrid Neural Parser and the BOUN Treebank", Institutsversammlung, IMS, Universität Stuttgart, Stuttgart, Germany (4 Nov, 2020)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Computer Engineering Department, Boğaziçi University

CMPE150, Introduction to Computing, 2019-2020, 2. Semester

Course Assistant

Computer Engineering Department, Boğaziçi University

CMPE493, Introduction to Information Retrieval, 2015-2016, 1. Semester

Honors and Awards	2019-2020	Tubitak ARDEB 2232 - Scholarship from The International Fellowship for Outstanding Researchers Program
	2018-2019	Tubitak ARDEB 1005 - Scholarship from National New Ideas and Products Research Support Program
	2014-2019	Tubitak BIDEB 2211 - Scholarship for PhD Students
	2012-2014	Tubitak BIDEB 2228 - MSc and PhD Scholarship for Senior Undergraduate Students
	2012	Highest honors in Engineering Faculty, Boğaziçi University

COMPUTER SKILLS

- Python, Java, C, C++
- Matlab, Latex, Perl
- Deep neural networks, Transformers, NLP applications
- OS: Linux-based systems, Windows

Relevant Skills

 ${\bf Languages:} \qquad {\bf Turkish} \ ({\it Native}), \ {\bf English} \ ({\it Advanced}), \ {\bf German} \ ({\it Intermediate})$

Graduate Coursework

- Artificial Neural Networks
- Pattern Recognition
- Natural Language Processing
- Information Retrieval
- Bioinformatics
- Artificial Intelligence
- Bayesian Statistics
- Monte Carlo Methods
- Biometrics
- Statistics in Mobile Computing
- Wearable Computing